11.002. 2. Cetanākaraṇīyasutta - 2. Making a Wish

1. Nissayavagga - 1. Dependence

“Sīlavato, bhikkhave, sīlasampannassa na cetanāya karaṇīyaṃ:

“Mendicants, an ethical person, who has fulfilled ethical conduct, need not make a wish:

‘avippaṭisāro me uppajjatū’ti.

‘May I have no regrets!’

Dhammatā esā, bhikkhave, yaṃ sīlavato sīlasampannassa avippaṭisāro uppajjati.

It’s only natural that an ethical person has no regrets.

Avippaṭisārissa, bhikkhave, na cetanāya karaṇīyaṃ:

When you have no regrets you need not make a wish:

‘pāmojjaṃ me uppajjatū’ti.

‘May I feel joy!’

Dhammatā esā, bhikkhave, yaṃ avippaṭisārissa pāmojjaṃ uppajjati.

It’s only natural that joy springs up when you have no regrets.

Pamuditassa, bhikkhave, na cetanāya karaṇīyaṃ:

When you feel joy you need not make a wish:

‘pīti me uppajjatū’ti.

‘May I experience rapture!’

Dhammatā esā, bhikkhave, yaṃ pamuditassa pīti uppajjati.

It’s only natural that rapture arises when you’re joyful.

Pītimanassa, bhikkhave, na cetanāya karaṇīyaṃ:

When your mind is full of rapture you need not make a wish:

‘kāyo me passambhatū’ti.

‘May my body become tranquil!’

Dhammatā esā, bhikkhave, yaṃ pītimanassa kāyo passambhati.

It’s only natural that your body becomes tranquil when your mind is full of rapture.

Passaddhakāyassa, bhikkhave, na cetanāya karaṇīyaṃ:

When your body is tranquil you need not make a wish:

‘sukhaṃ vediyāmī’ti.

‘May I feel bliss!’

Dhammatā esā, bhikkhave, yaṃ passaddhakāyo sukhaṃ vediyati.

It’s only natural to feel bliss when your body is tranquil.

Sukhino, bhikkhave, na cetanāya karaṇīyaṃ:

When you feel bliss you need not make a wish:

‘cittaṃ me samādhiyatū’ti.

‘May my mind be immersed in samādhi!’

Dhammatā esā, bhikkhave, yaṃ sukhino cittaṃ samādhiyati.

It’s only natural for the mind to become immersed in samādhi when you feel bliss.

Samāhitassa, bhikkhave, na cetanāya karaṇīyaṃ:

When your mind is immersed in samādhi you need not make a wish:

‘yathābhūtaṃ jānāmi passāmī’ti.

‘May I truly know and see!’

Dhammatā esā, bhikkhave, yaṃ samāhito yathābhūtaṃ jānāti passati.

It’s only natural to truly know and see when your mind is immersed in samādhi.

Yathābhūtaṃ, bhikkhave, jānato passato na cetanāya karaṇīyaṃ:

When you truly know and see you need not make a wish:

‘nibbindāmī’ti.

‘May I grow disillusioned!’

Dhammatā esā, bhikkhave, yaṃ yathābhūtaṃ jānaṃ passaṃ nibbindati.

It’s only natural to grow disillusioned when you truly know and see.

Nibbinnassa, bhikkhave, na cetanāya karaṇīyaṃ:

When you’re disillusioned you need not make a wish:

‘virajjāmī’ti.

‘May I become dispassionate!’

Dhammatā esā, bhikkhave, yaṃ nibbinno virajjati.

It’s only natural to grow dispassionate when you’re disillusioned.

Virattassa, bhikkhave, na cetanāya karaṇīyaṃ:

When you’re dispassionate you need not make a wish:

‘vimuttiñāṇadassanaṃ sacchikaromī’ti.

‘May I realize the knowledge and vision of freedom!’

Dhammatā esā, bhikkhave, yaṃ viratto vimuttiñāṇadassanaṃ sacchikaroti.

It’s only natural to realize the knowledge and vision of freedom when you’re dispassionate.

Iti kho, bhikkhave, virāgo vimuttiñāṇadassanattho vimuttiñāṇadassanānisaṃso, nibbidā virāgatthā virāgānisaṃsā, yathābhūtañāṇadassanaṃ nibbidatthaṃ nibbidānisaṃsaṃ, samādhi yathābhūtañāṇadassanattho yathābhūtañāṇadassanānisaṃso, sukhaṃ samādhatthaṃ samādhānisaṃsaṃ, passaddhi sukhatthā sukhānisaṃsā, pīti passaddhatthā passaddhānisaṃsā, pāmojjaṃ pītatthaṃ pītānisaṃsaṃ, avippaṭisāro pāmojjattho pāmojjānisaṃso, kusalāni sīlāni avippaṭisāratthāni avippaṭisārānisaṃsāni.

And so, mendicants, the knowledge and vision of freedom is the purpose and benefit of dispassion. Dispassion is the purpose and benefit of disillusionment. Disillusionment is the purpose and benefit of truly knowing and seeing. Truly knowing and seeing is the purpose and benefit of immersion. Immersion is the purpose and benefit of bliss. Bliss is the purpose and benefit of tranquility. Tranquility is the purpose and benefit of rapture. Rapture is the purpose and benefit of joy. Joy is the purpose and benefit of not having regrets. Not having regrets is the purpose and benefit of skillful ethics.

Iti kho, bhikkhave, dhammā dhamme abhisandenti, dhammā dhamme paripūrenti apārā pāraṃ gamanāyā”ti.

And so, mendicants, good qualities flow on and fill up from one to the other, for going from the near shore to the far shore.”

Dutiyaṃ.

11.007. 7. Saññāsutta - 7. Percipient

1. Nissayavagga - 1. Dependence

Atha kho āyasmā ānando yena bhagavā tenupasaṅkami; upasaṅkamitvā bhagavantaṃ abhivādetvā ekamantaṃ nisīdi. Ekamantaṃ nisinno kho āyasmā ānando bhagavantaṃ etadavoca:

Then Venerable Ānanda went up to the Buddha, bowed, sat down to one side, and said to him:

“Siyā nu kho, bhante, bhikkhuno tathārūpo samādhipaṭilābho yathā neva pathaviyaṃ pathavisaññī assa, na āpasmiṃ āposaññī assa, na tejasmiṃ tejosaññī assa, na vāyasmiṃ vāyosaññī assa, na ākāsānañcāyatane ākāsānañcāyatanasaññī assa, na viññāṇañcāyatane viññāṇañcāyatanasaññī assa, na ākiñcaññāyatane ākiñcaññāyatanasaññī assa, na nevasaññānāsaññāyatane nevasaññānāsaññāyatanasaññī assa, na idhaloke idhalokasaññī assa, na paraloke paralokasaññī assa, yampidaṃ diṭṭhaṃ sutaṃ mutaṃ viññātaṃ pattaṃ pariyesitaṃ anuvicaritaṃ manasā, tatrāpi na saññī assa; saññī ca pana assā”ti?

“Could it be, sir, that a mendicant might gain a state of immersion like this? They wouldn’t perceive earth in earth, water in water, fire in fire, or air in air. And they wouldn’t perceive the dimension of infinite space in the dimension of infinite space, the dimension of infinite consciousness in the dimension of infinite consciousness, the dimension of nothingness in the dimension of nothingness, or the dimension of neither perception nor non-perception in the dimension of neither perception nor non-perception. They wouldn’t perceive this world in this world, or the other world in the other world. And they wouldn’t perceive what is seen, heard, thought, known, attained, sought, or explored by the mind. And yet they would still perceive.”

“Siyā, ānanda, bhikkhuno tathārūpo samādhipaṭilābho yathā neva pathaviyaṃ pathavisaññī assa, na āpasmiṃ āposaññī assa, na tejasmiṃ tejosaññī assa, na vāyasmiṃ vāyosaññī assa, na ākāsānañcāyatane ākāsānañcāyatanasaññī assa, na viññāṇañcāyatane viññāṇañcāyatanasaññī assa, na ākiñcaññāyatane ākiñcaññāyatanasaññī assa, na nevasaññānāsaññāyatane nevasaññānāsaññāyatanasaññī assa, na idhaloke idhalokasaññī assa, na paraloke paralokasaññī assa, yampidaṃ diṭṭhaṃ sutaṃ mutaṃ viññātaṃ pattaṃ pariyesitaṃ anuvicaritaṃ manasā, tatrāpi na saññī assa; saññī ca pana assā”ti.

“It could be, Ānanda, that a mendicant might gain a state of immersion like this. They wouldn’t perceive earth in earth, water in water, fire in fire, or air in air. And they wouldn’t perceive the dimension of infinite space in the dimension of infinite space, the dimension of infinite consciousness in the dimension of infinite consciousness, the dimension of nothingness in the dimension of nothingness, or the dimension of neither perception nor non-perception in the dimension of neither perception nor non-perception. They wouldn’t perceive this world in this world, or the other world in the other world. And they wouldn’t perceive what is seen, heard, thought, known, attained, sought, or explored by the mind. And yet they would still perceive.”

“Yathā kathaṃ pana, bhante, siyā bhikkhuno tathārūpo samādhipaṭilābho yathā neva pathaviyaṃ pathavisaññī assa, na āpasmiṃ āposaññī assa, na tejasmiṃ tejosaññī assa, na vāyasmiṃ vāyosaññī assa, na ākāsānañcāyatane ākāsānañcāyatanasaññī assa, na viññāṇañcāyatane viññāṇañcāyatanasaññī assa, na ākiñcaññāyatane ākiñcaññāyatanasaññī assa, na nevasaññānāsaññāyatane nevasaññānāsaññāyatanasaññī assa, na idhaloke idhalokasaññī assa, na paraloke paralokasaññī assa, yampidaṃ diṭṭhaṃ sutaṃ mutaṃ viññātaṃ pattaṃ pariyesitaṃ anuvicaritaṃ manasā, tatrāpi na saññī assa, saññī ca pana assā”ti.

“But how could this be, sir?”

“Idhānanda, bhikkhu evaṃsaññī hoti:

“Ānanda, it’s when a mendicant perceives:

‘etaṃ santaṃ etaṃ paṇītaṃ, yadidaṃ sabbasaṅkhārasamatho sabbūpadhipaṭinissaggo taṇhākkhayo virāgo nirodho nibbānan’ti.

‘This is peaceful; this is sublime—that is, the stilling of all activities, the letting go of all attachments, the ending of craving, fading away, cessation, extinguishment.’

Evaṃ kho, ānanda, siyā bhikkhuno tathārūpo samādhipaṭilābho yathā neva pathaviyaṃ pathavisaññī assa, na āpasmiṃ āposaññī assa, na tejasmiṃ tejosaññī assa, na vāyasmiṃ vāyosaññī assa, na ākāsānañcāyatane ākāsānañcāyatanasaññī assa, na viññāṇañcāyatane viññāṇañcāyatanasaññī assa, na ākiñcaññāyatane ākiñcaññāyatanasaññī assa, na nevasaññānāsaññāyatane nevasaññānāsaññāyatanasaññī assa, na idhaloke idhalokasaññī assa, na paraloke paralokasaññī assa, yampidaṃ diṭṭhaṃ sutaṃ mutaṃ viññātaṃ pattaṃ pariyesitaṃ anuvicaritaṃ manasā, tatrāpi na saññī assa, saññī ca pana assā”ti.

That’s how a mendicant might gain a state of immersion like this. They wouldn’t perceive earth in earth, water in water, fire in fire, or air in air. And they wouldn’t perceive the dimension of infinite space in the dimension of infinite space, the dimension of infinite consciousness in the dimension of infinite consciousness, the dimension of nothingness in the dimension of nothingness, or the dimension of neither perception nor non-perception in the dimension of neither perception nor non-perception. They wouldn’t perceive this world in this world, or the other world in the other world. And they wouldn’t perceive what is seen, heard, thought, known, attained, sought, or explored by the mind. And yet they would still perceive.”

Atha kho āyasmā ānando bhagavato bhāsitaṃ abhinanditvā anumoditvā uṭṭhāyāsanā bhagavantaṃ abhivādetvā padakkhiṇaṃ katvā yenāyasmā sāriputto tenupasaṅkami; upasaṅkamitvā āyasmatā sāriputtena saddhiṃ sammodi.

And then Ānanda approved and agreed with what the Buddha said. He got up from his seat, bowed, and respectfully circled the Buddha, keeping him on his right. Then he went up to Venerable Sāriputta, and exchanged greetings with him.

Sammodanīyaṃ kathaṃ sāraṇīyaṃ vītisāretvā ekamantaṃ nisīdi. Ekamantaṃ nisinno kho āyasmā ānando āyasmantaṃ sāriputtaṃ etadavoca:

When the greetings and polite conversation were over, he sat down to one side and said to Sāriputta:

“Siyā nu kho, āvuso sāriputta, bhikkhuno tathārūpo samādhipaṭilābho yathā neva pathaviyaṃ pathavisaññī assa … pe … yampidaṃ diṭṭhaṃ sutaṃ mutaṃ viññātaṃ pattaṃ pariyesitaṃ anuvicaritaṃ manasā, tatrāpi na saññī assa, saññī pana assā”ti.

“Could it be, reverend Sāriputta, that a mendicant might gain a state of immersion like this? They wouldn’t perceive earth in earth … And they wouldn’t perceive what is seen, heard, thought, known, attained, sought, or explored by the mind. And yet they would still perceive.”

“Siyā, āvuso ānanda, bhikkhuno tathārūpo samādhipaṭilābho yathā neva pathaviyaṃ pathavisaññī assa … pe … yampidaṃ diṭṭhaṃ sutaṃ mutaṃ viññātaṃ pattaṃ pariyesitaṃ anuvicaritaṃ manasā, tatrāpi na saññī assa, saññī ca pana assā”ti.

“It could be, Reverend Ānanda.”

“Yathā kathaṃ panāvuso sāriputta, siyā bhikkhuno tathārūpo samādhipaṭilābho yathā neva pathaviyaṃ pathavisaññī assa … pe … yampidaṃ diṭṭhaṃ sutaṃ mutaṃ viññātaṃ pattaṃ pariyesitaṃ anuvicaritaṃ manasā, tatrāpi na saññī assa, saññī ca pana assā”ti?

“But how could this be?”

“Idha, āvuso ānanda, bhikkhu evaṃsaññī hoti:

“Ānanda, it’s when a mendicant perceives:

‘etaṃ santaṃ etaṃ paṇītaṃ, yadidaṃ sabbasaṅkhārasamatho sabbūpadhipaṭinissaggo taṇhākkhayo virāgo nirodho nibbānan’ti.

‘This is peaceful; this is sublime—that is, the stilling of all activities, the letting go of all attachments, the ending of craving, fading away, cessation, extinguishment.’

Evaṃ kho, āvuso ānanda, siyā bhikkhuno tathārūpo samādhipaṭilābho yathā neva pathaviyaṃ pathavisaññī assa … pe … yampidaṃ diṭṭhaṃ sutaṃ mutaṃ viññātaṃ pattaṃ pariyesitaṃ anuvicaritaṃ manasā, tatrāpi na saññī assa, saññī ca pana assā”ti.

That’s how a mendicant might gain a state of immersion like this. They wouldn’t perceive earth in earth … And they wouldn’t perceive what is seen, heard, thought, known, attained, sought, or explored by the mind. And yet they would still perceive.”

“Acchariyaṃ, āvuso, abbhutaṃ, āvuso.

“It’s incredible, it’s amazing!

Yatra hi nāma satthu ceva sāvakassa ca atthena attho byañjanena byañjanaṃ saṃsandissati samessati na viggayhissati, yadidaṃ aggapadasmiṃ.

How the meaning and the phrasing of the teacher and the disciple fit together and agree without conflict when it comes to the chief matter!

Idānāhaṃ, āvuso, bhagavantaṃ upasaṅkamitvā etamatthaṃ apucchiṃ.

Just now I went to the Buddha and asked him about this matter.

Bhagavāpi me etehi akkharehi etehi padehi etehi byañjanehi etamatthaṃ byākāsi, seyyathāpi āyasmā sāriputto.

And the Buddha explained it to me in this manner, with these words and phrases, just like Venerable Sāriputta.

Acchariyaṃ, āvuso, abbhutaṃ, āvuso.

It’s incredible, it’s amazing!

Yatra hi nāma satthu ceva sāvakassa ca atthena attho byañjanena byañjanaṃ saṃsandissati samessati na viggayhissati, yadidaṃ aggapadasmin”ti.

How the meaning and the phrasing of the teacher and the disciple fit together and agree without conflict when it comes to the chief matter!”

Sattamaṃ.

11.013. 13. Nandiyasutta - 13. With Nandiya

2. Anussativagga - 2. Recollection

Ekaṃ samayaṃ bhagavā sakkesu viharati kapilavatthusmiṃ nigrodhārāme.

At one time the Buddha was staying in the land of the Sakyans, near Kapilavatthu in the Banyan Tree Monastery.

Tena kho pana samayena bhagavā sāvatthiyaṃ vassāvāsaṃ upagantukāmo hoti.

Now at that time the Buddha wanted to commence the rains residence at Sāvatthī.

Assosi kho nandiyo sakko:

Nandiya the Sakyan heard about this,

“bhagavā kira sāvatthiyaṃ vassāvāsaṃ upagantukāmo”ti.

Atha kho nandiyassa sakkassa etadahosi:

and thought,

“yannūnāhampi sāvatthiyaṃ vassāvāsaṃ upagaccheyyaṃ.

“Why don’t I also commence the rains residence at Sāvatthī.

Tattha kammantañceva adhiṭṭhahissāmi, bhagavantañca lacchāmi kālena kālaṃ dassanāyā”ti.

There I can apply myself to my work and from time to time get to see the Buddha.”

Atha kho bhagavā sāvatthiyaṃ vassāvāsaṃ upagacchi.

So the Buddha commenced the rains residence in Sāvatthī,

Nandiyopi kho sakko sāvatthiyaṃ vassāvāsaṃ upagacchi.

and so did Nandiya.

Tattha kammantañceva adhiṭṭhāsi, bhagavantañca labhi kālena kālaṃ dassanāya.

There he applied himself to his work and from time to time got to see the Buddha.

Tena kho pana samayena sambahulā bhikkhū bhagavato cīvarakammaṃ karonti:

At that time several mendicants were making a robe for the Buddha, thinking that

“niṭṭhitacīvaro bhagavā temāsaccayena cārikaṃ pakkamissatī”ti.

when his robe was finished and the three months of the rains residence had passed the Buddha would set out wandering.

Assosi kho nandiyo sakko:

Nandiya the Sakyan heard about this.

“sambahulā kira bhikkhū bhagavato cīvarakammaṃ karonti:

‘niṭṭhitacīvaro bhagavā temāsaccayena cārikaṃ pakkamissatī’”ti.

Atha kho nandiyo sakko yena bhagavā tenupasaṅkami; upasaṅkamitvā bhagavantaṃ abhivādetvā ekamantaṃ nisīdi. Ekamantaṃ nisinno kho nandiyo sakko bhagavantaṃ etadavoca:

He went up to the Buddha, bowed, sat down to one side, and said to him:

“sutaṃ metaṃ, bhante:

“Sir, I have heard that

‘sambahulā kira bhikkhū bhagavato cīvarakammaṃ karonti—

several mendicants are making a robe for the Buddha, thinking that

niṭṭhitacīvaro bhagavā temāsaccayena cārikaṃ pakkamissatī’ti.

when his robe was finished and the three months of the rains residence had passed the Buddha would set out wandering.

Tesaṃ no, bhante, nānāvihārehi viharataṃ kenassa vihārena vihātabban”ti?

Now, we spend our life in various ways. Which of these should we practice?”

“Sādhu sādhu, nandiya.

“Good, good Nandiya!

Etaṃ kho, nandiya, tumhākaṃ patirūpaṃ kulaputtānaṃ, yaṃ tumhe tathāgataṃ upasaṅkamitvā puccheyyātha:

It’s appropriate that gentlemen such as you come to me and ask:

‘tesaṃ no, bhante, nānāvihārehi viharataṃ kenassa vihārena vihātabban’ti?

‘We spend our life in various ways. Which of these should we practice?’

Saddho kho, nandiya, ārādhako hoti, no assaddho;

The faithful succeed, not the faithless.

sīlavā ārādhako hoti, no dussīlo;

The ethical succeed, not the unethical.

āraddhavīriyo ārādhako hoti, no kusīto;

The energetic succeed, not the lazy.

upaṭṭhitassati ārādhako hoti, no muṭṭhassati;

The mindful succeed, not the unmindful.

samāhito ārādhako hoti, no asamāhito;

Those with immersion succeed, not those without immersion.

paññavā ārādhako hoti, no duppañño.

The wise succeed, not the witless.

Imesu kho te, nandiya, chasu dhammesu patiṭṭhāya pañcasu dhammesu ajjhattaṃ sati upaṭṭhāpetabbā.

When you’re grounded on these six things, go on to develop five further things.

Idha tvaṃ, nandiya, tathāgataṃ anussareyyāsi:

Firstly, you should recollect the Realized One:

‘itipi so bhagavā arahaṃ sammāsambuddho vijjācaraṇasampanno sugato lokavidū anuttaro purisadammasārathi, satthā devamanussānaṃ buddho bhagavā’ti.

‘That Blessed One is perfected, a fully awakened Buddha, accomplished in knowledge and conduct, holy, knower of the world, supreme guide for those who wish to train, teacher of gods and humans, awakened, blessed.’

Iti kho te, nandiya, tathāgataṃ ārabbha ajjhattaṃ sati upaṭṭhāpetabbā.

In this way you should establish mindfulness internally based on the Realized One.

Puna caparaṃ tvaṃ, nandiya, dhammaṃ anussareyyāsi:

Furthermore, you should recollect the teaching:

‘svākkhāto bhagavatā dhammo sandiṭṭhiko akāliko ehipassiko opaneyyiko paccattaṃ veditabbo viññūhī’ti.

‘The teaching is well explained by the Buddha—visible in this very life, immediately effective, inviting inspection, relevant, so that sensible people can know it for themselves.’

Iti kho te, nandiya, dhammaṃ ārabbha ajjhattaṃ sati upaṭṭhāpetabbā.

In this way you should establish mindfulness internally based on the teaching.

Puna caparaṃ tvaṃ, nandiya, kalyāṇamitte anussareyyāsi:

Furthermore, you should recollect your good friends:

‘lābhā vata me, suladdhaṃ vata me,

‘I’m fortunate, so very fortunate,

yassa me kalyāṇamittā anukampakā atthakāmā ovādakā anusāsakā’ti.

to have good friends who advise and instruct me out of kindness and compassion.’

Iti kho te, nandiya, kalyāṇamitte ārabbha ajjhattaṃ sati upaṭṭhāpetabbā.

In this way you should establish mindfulness internally based on good friends.

Puna caparaṃ tvaṃ, nandiya, attano cāgaṃ anussareyyāsi:

Furthermore, you should recollect your own generosity:

‘lābhā vata me, suladdhaṃ vata me,

‘I’m so fortunate, so very fortunate.

yohaṃ maccheramalapariyuṭṭhitāya pajāya vigatamalamaccherena cetasā agāraṃ ajjhāvasāmi muttacāgo payatapāṇi vossaggarato yācayogo dānasaṃvibhāgarato’ti.

Among people with hearts full of the stain of stinginess I live at home rid of stinginess, freely generous, open-handed, loving to let go, committed to charity, loving to give and to share.’

Iti kho te, nandiya, cāgaṃ ārabbha ajjhattaṃ sati upaṭṭhāpetabbā.

In this way you should establish mindfulness internally based on generosity.

Puna caparaṃ tvaṃ, nandiya, devatā anussareyyāsi:

Furthermore, you should recollect the deities:

‘yā devatā atikkammeva kabaḷīkārāhārabhakkhānaṃ devatānaṃ sahabyataṃ aññataraṃ manomayaṃ kāyaṃ upapannā, tā karaṇīyaṃ attano na samanupassanti katassa vā paticayaṃ’.

‘There are deities who, surpassing the company of deities that consume solid food, are reborn in a certain host of mind-made deities. They don’t see in themselves anything more to do, or anything that needs improvement.’

Seyyathāpi, nandiya, bhikkhu asamayavimutto karaṇīyaṃ attano na samanupassati katassa vā paticayaṃ;

An irreversibly freed mendicant doesn’t see in themselves anything more to do, or anything that needs improvement.

evamevaṃ kho, nandiya, yā tā devatā atikkammeva kabaḷīkārāhārabhakkhānaṃ devatānaṃ sahabyataṃ aññataraṃ manomayaṃ kāyaṃ upapannā, tā karaṇīyaṃ attano na samanupassanti katassa vā paticayaṃ.

In the same way, Nandiya, there are deities who, surpassing the company of deities that consume solid food, are reborn in a certain host of mind-made deities. They don’t see in themselves anything more to do, or anything that needs improvement.

Iti kho te, nandiya, devatā ārabbha ajjhattaṃ sati upaṭṭhāpetabbā.

In this way you should establish mindfulness internally based on the deities.

Imehi kho, nandiya, ekādasahi dhammehi samannāgato ariyasāvako pajahateva pāpake akusale dhamme, na upādiyati.

A noble disciple who has these eleven qualities gives up bad, unskillful qualities and doesn’t cling to them.

Seyyathāpi, nandiya, kumbho nikkujjo vamateva udakaṃ, no vantaṃ paccāvamati;

It’s like when a pot full of water is tipped over, so the water drains out and doesn’t go back in.

seyyathāpi vā pana, nandiya, sukkhe tiṇadāye aggi mutto ḍahaññeva gacchati, no daḍḍhaṃ paccudāvattati;

Suppose there was an uncontrolled fire. It advances burning up dry woodlands and doesn’t go back over what it has burned.

evamevaṃ kho, nandiya, imehi ekādasahi dhammehi samannāgato ariyasāvako pajahateva pāpake akusale dhamme, na upādiyatī”ti.

In the same way, a noble disciple who has these eleven qualities gives up bad, unskillful qualities and doesn’t cling to them.”

Tatiyaṃ.

11.020. 20. Tatiyasamādhisutta - 20. Immersion (3rd)

2. Anussativagga - 2. Recollection

Atha kho sambahulā bhikkhū yenāyasmā sāriputto tenupasaṅkamiṃsu; upasaṅkamitvā āyasmatā sāriputtena saddhiṃ sammodiṃsu.

And then several mendicants went up to Venerable Sāriputta, and exchanged greetings with him.

Sammodanīyaṃ kathaṃ sāraṇīyaṃ vītisāretvā ekamantaṃ nisīdiṃsu. Ekamantaṃ nisinnā kho te bhikkhū āyasmantaṃ sāriputtaṃ etadavocuṃ:

When the greetings and polite conversation were over, they sat down to one side and said to him:

“Siyā nu kho, āvuso sāriputta, bhikkhuno tathārūpo samādhipaṭilābho yathā neva pathaviyaṃ pathavisaññī assa … pe … yampidaṃ diṭṭhaṃ sutaṃ mutaṃ viññātaṃ pattaṃ pariyesitaṃ anuvicaritaṃ manasā tatrāpi na saññī assa; saññī ca pana assā”ti?

“Could it be, reverend, that a mendicant might gain a state of immersion like this? They wouldn’t perceive earth in earth, water in water, fire in fire, or air in air. And they wouldn’t perceive the dimension of infinite space in the dimension of infinite space, the dimension of infinite consciousness in the dimension of infinite consciousness, the dimension of nothingness in the dimension of nothingness, or the dimension of neither perception nor non-perception in the dimension of neither perception nor non-perception. They wouldn’t perceive this world in this world, or the other world in the other world. And they wouldn’t perceive what is seen, heard, thought, known, attained, sought, or explored by the mind. And yet they would still perceive.”

“Siyā, āvuso, bhikkhuno tathārūpo samādhipaṭilābho yathā neva pathaviyaṃ pathavisaññī assa … pe … yampidaṃ diṭṭhaṃ sutaṃ mutaṃ viññātaṃ pattaṃ pariyesitaṃ anuvicaritaṃ manasā tatrāpi na saññī assa; saññī ca pana assā”ti.

“It could be, reverends.”

“Yathā kathaṃ pana, āvuso sāriputta, siyā bhikkhuno tathārūpo samādhipaṭilābho yathā neva pathaviyaṃ pathavisaññī assa … pe … yampidaṃ diṭṭhaṃ sutaṃ mutaṃ viññātaṃ pattaṃ pariyesitaṃ anuvicaritaṃ manasā tatrāpi na saññī assa; saññī ca pana assā”ti?

“But how could this be?”

“Idha, āvuso, bhikkhu evaṃsaññī hoti:

“It’s when a mendicant perceives:

‘etaṃ santaṃ etaṃ paṇītaṃ, yadidaṃ sabbasaṅkhārasamatho sabbūpadhipaṭinissaggo taṇhākkhayo virāgo nirodho nibbānan’ti.

‘This is peaceful; this is sublime—that is, the stilling of all activities, the letting go of all attachments, the ending of craving, fading away, cessation, extinguishment.’

Evaṃ kho, āvuso, siyā bhikkhuno tathārūpo samādhipaṭilābho yathā neva pathaviyaṃ pathavisaññī assa … pe … yampidaṃ diṭṭhaṃ sutaṃ mutaṃ viññātaṃ pattaṃ pariyesitaṃ anuvicaritaṃ manasā tatrāpi na saññī assa; saññī ca pana assā”ti.

That’s how a mendicant might gain a state of immersion like this. They wouldn’t perceive earth in earth, water in water, fire in fire, or air in air. And they wouldn’t perceive the dimension of infinite space in the dimension of infinite space, the dimension of infinite consciousness in the dimension of infinite consciousness, the dimension of nothingness in the dimension of nothingness, or the dimension of neither perception nor non-perception in the dimension of neither perception nor non-perception. They wouldn’t perceive this world in this world, or the other world in the other world. And they wouldn’t perceive what is seen, heard, thought, known, attained, sought, or explored by the mind. And yet they would still perceive.”

Dasamaṃ.

11.022-29. Sāmaññavagga - 3. Similarity

Paṭhamapaṇṇāsaka - The First Fifty

AN 11.22–29

22–29

“Ekādasahi, bhikkhave, aṅgehi samannāgato gopālako abhabbo gogaṇaṃ pariharituṃ phātiṃ kātuṃ.

“Mendicants, a cowherd with eleven factors can’t maintain and expand a herd of cattle.

Katamehi ekādasahi?

What eleven?

Idha, bhikkhave, gopālako na rūpaññū hoti, na lakkhaṇakusalo hoti, na āsāṭikaṃ hāretā hoti, na vaṇaṃ paṭicchādetā hoti, na dhūmaṃ kattā hoti, na titthaṃ jānāti, na pītaṃ jānāti, na vīthiṃ jānāti, na gocarakusalo hoti, anavasesadohī ca hoti, ye te usabhā gopitaro gopariṇāyakā te na atirekapūjāya pūjetā hoti—

It’s when a cowherd doesn’t know form, is unskilled in characteristics, doesn’t pick out flies’ eggs, doesn’t dress wounds, doesn’t smoke out pests, doesn’t know the ford, doesn’t know satisfaction, doesn’t know the trail, is not skilled in pastures, milks dry, and doesn’t show extra respect to the bulls who are fathers and leaders of the herd.

imehi kho, bhikkhave, ekādasahi aṅgehi samannāgato gopālako abhabbo gogaṇaṃ pariharituṃ phātiṃ kātuṃ.

A cowherd with these eleven factors can’t maintain and expand a herd of cattle.

Evamevaṃ kho, bhikkhave, ekādasahi dhammehi samannāgato bhikkhu abhabbo cakkhusmiṃ aniccānupassī viharituṃ…

In the same way, a mendicant with eleven qualities can’t meditate observing impermanence in the eye …

pe…

abhabbo cakkhusmiṃ dukkhānupassī viharituṃ…

suffering …

abhabbo cakkhusmiṃ anattānupassī viharituṃ…

not-self …

abhabbo cakkhusmiṃ khayānupassī viharituṃ…

ending …

abhabbo cakkhusmiṃ vayānupassī viharituṃ…

vanishing …

abhabbo cakkhusmiṃ virāgānupassī viharituṃ…

fading away …

abhabbo cakkhusmiṃ nirodhānupassī viharituṃ…

cessation …

abhabbo cakkhusmiṃ paṭinissaggānupassī viharituṃ”.

letting go …”